Greetings and thank you. I wanted to
first express my appreciation to
uh the National Bank of Cambodia,
Governor Chea Chanto, and also Her
Excellency Chea Serey, the Assistant
Governor and Director General of Central
Banking.
Um and to the Association of Banks of
Cambodia, the Chairman Dr. In Channy.
Um to all of you for your leadership in
promoting and organizing this important
conference uh with the Association of
Finance and Technology of Cambodia.
I'm honored to be part of this
conference and to be joining uh such a
distinguished group of uh speakers
representing uh very important
organizations.
Um you gave me a difficult assignment,
however, because talking about uh the
topic of going green, the trends and
drivers of sustainable
uh banking and investment in only 20
minutes is a very very challenging task.
Um and I think you know all have been to
various meetings and conferences, you
know that typically these take hours and
sometimes days to talk about these
topics.
So, I will be talking about, as you
could imagine, uh some very high-level
um discussions and some of the themes.
If I can share the screen, let me make
sure I can. I would like to to keep the
uh discussion to a very high level um
and start with let's talk with the
global trends and drivers.
Um I I think we can all agree that um
the probably the most fundamental uh
global trend and driver that leads us
into this question of sustainability and
sustainable finance starts with the
whole trend of globalization.
Um if we think about um history, um
it's only really in the last 20 years
that we can say
that globalization has changed um just
basically everything that we do.
Um and many of those uh the impacts of
globalization have been positive. Uh
increasing trade and investment has led
to rising incomes, it's led to improving
health and longer lifespans.
It's led to more people being connected
uh to information and education um and
having a greater global sharing of
knowledge. But, it's also led to um and
and not solved certain problems, but
it's also increased certain problems
that we still find ourselves having to
deal with today all across the world.
Whether those are problems of
inequality, uh uh discrimination that
still exists, pollution that's um it
plaguing cities, or um natural disasters
that are coming and increasing as a
result of climate change. This year, I
think we've all been even more uh aware
of this challenge of shared problems
that come that face us today in a
connected world because of the pandemic.
Um obviously, um everybody's been
affected by this, but what drives home
this connectedness is
countries that didn't have high rates of
infection. I could think of Thailand, I
could think of Cambodia. Are still
impacted because other places which have
higher rates of infection have had to
alter their behavior, whether that means
they aren't traveling or they aren't
consuming certain products or whatever.
So, we see that even if uh my I was uh I
I was sick, you weren't sick, but you
still suffer because of my sickness. And
so, we're definitely more connected
today, more aware of this.
The manifestation of that awareness, the
best example, is the fact that we've now
as a globe embraced a set of goals.
So, there are 17 Sustainable Development
Goals that that that you could say
describe today global priorities. And
these are the priorities of of of
virtually every country on the planet
and we're now measuring ourselves
against these various goals and 169
targets that underlie these goals.
Um
The interesting aspect that I think is
most fundamental, we come back to the
question of how this is impacting
finance and how this is impacting
business, is that
the Sustainable Development Goals, we
all realize now, are not just the jobs
of governments.
We all, all parts of society, have to
embrace a responsibility for doing our
part in trying to achieve these goals.
And I think that captures a fundamental
change, what I would call a
revolutionary change that's happened
literally within the last num few years
um in what business describes as its
purpose.
Um
if in and I'm mean this not only in the
way we feel and how we're actually
working, but formally describes as a
purpose. Uh if we look at the statements
by the British Academy or the Business
Roundtable as to the what is the purpose
of a business, we our purpose, according
to the British Academy, is to solve the
problems of people and planet profitably
and not profit from causing problems. We
look at the Business Roundtable,
we see a stakeholder approach, not only
customers and shareholders. I mean, when
I started work, my first full-time job
probably 40 years ago, uh I was I
thought the purpose of business was to
make good products and services, comply
with the law, and to make profits for
shareholders. If someone had said to me,
"Our job is also to make society better
and to solve major social problems," I
would not have necessarily understood
why that was the case. But, today that
is in fact what we've all embraced, I
think, across the business community,
that we have a broader purpose. And that
purpose is to try to make a positive
impact. And that phenomenon parallels
and is reinforced by the the concept of
ESG, which I'm sure you've talked about
already in the conference and I'm sure
will be talked about more on the panel
that follows.
But, the ESG concept, a framework if you
will, is now driving corporate behavior
and it's driving investment behavior
pretty much across the planet. We may
not be feeling it quite as intensively
in Asia up to this point, but I think we
all know that now in Asia this is a
rapidly increasing important topic.
The environmental, the social, and the
governance capabilities of a company
to manage its business and to make sure
that it can manage environmental risks
and it also its environmental impacts
and minimize those, to be able to manage
social risks and create social capital,
and be able to govern itself effectively
is is critical. And this phenomenon and
this framework is leading to a massive
change in how finance is being allocated
around the world. I think the numbers,
you can find various numbers, they're
all big numbers. Um
the number in this particular chart is
as of 2018 and it's only gotten bigger.
There were 30 there was 31 trillion
dollars invested with sustainable
mandates in the world. That could be
negative screens, uh investments not
going into certain places that are not
considered sustainable, or uh positive
screens, investing positively in
companies that are considered more
sustainable, but it's a large amount of
money.
Um
Eastspring Investments, which is
Prudential's asset management company,
manages about 220 billion dollars as of
the middle of this year,
signed up to the UN Principles for
Responsible Investment.
That set of principles, now over 3,000
organizations have signed directing
their investments to be responsible, and
that's over 100 trillion dollars of
global assets under management. So,
investment finance is flowing towards
sustainability.
But, it's not just investors that are
driving corporate behavior towards ESG
strong sustainable behavior, but also
the rating agencies, regulators. For
example, uh the National Bank of
Cambodia, I believe, is a member of the
Network for Greening the Financial
System, which is being organized by
central bankers around the world to make
sure that the banking sector is being
sensitive to sustainability risks,
especially climate risk, but and and is
managing itself in a way that will be
able to responsibly deal with those
risks and to promote a safer financial
system. The International Regulators of
Securities and Banking, IOSCO, the the
Regulators of Insurance, the
International Association of Insurance
Supervisors, also have work streams
working in the same regard. So, whatever
amount of trillions you see today that
are being directed towards
sustainability, I think that is only
going to increase in the future.
And the trend which I think the theme we
picked one theme globally that's going
to drive a lot of that in the next few
years, it will be around climate change.
I I Obviously, in this talk I can't go
into detail in why this is important,
but I think we all know that the current
trend of greenhouse gas emissions, if we
look at this line going straight up, we
know that that trend is not sustainable
and we've already reached a level of
concentration of carbon in the
atmosphere which is dangerous and we
that has to be brought down or we're
going to suffer serious issues, some of
which are listed on the right here.
And so, I think in the next few years
we're going to see increasing attention
on that. But, in our region,
unlike perhaps say in Europe or North
America where they reached a different
stage of development, in our region we
have to solve climate change and
solve growth issues and poverty issues
and financial access issues at the same
time. So, the challenge we have to
address in our region is greater.
There's no question about that.
And so, when we when I talk about how we
can address these things and and what
sustainable finance can do,
I put it in the contents of what I call
the gig economy. Now, when most people
in technology talk about the gig
economy, they're talking about the
short-term employment economy such as
Grab or Uber. When I say the gig
economy, I'm talking about green
inclusive growth.
We can't just be green, we also have to
grow. And we can't just grow because we
have to have inclusive growth. So, GIG.
And the themes I think will drive that
toward a gig economy, green inclusive
growing economy in Southeast Asia in the
next several years, decade, are five.
And I'll talk briefly touch on those
five themes. First, green bonds and
sustainable infrastructure.
Um I think we're all, um you know, in
the financial industry, we're very
attuned to the very large projections of
finance needed for infrastructure in the
future in this region. Over $3 trillion
projected from 2016 to 2030 by Asia
Development Bank, which is going to be
needed for infrastructure. And of
course, that infrastructure needs to be
sustainable and resilient, and it has to
has to be moving and being financed fast
enough to deal with a rapidly urbanizing
society. 70 million people moving to
cities are are are growth of population
in cities in ASEAN alone
between 2020 and 2030. That's about It's
19,000 people a week increasing in urban
environment. So, power, transportation,
uh water, sanitation, and and every
education, uh schools and hospitals, et
cetera. A huge need for that. And that
needs to be done sustainably. So, so
that's number one theme I think that's
we're all going to have to work very
hard to to meet that challenge.
Secondly, financing energy transition to
move from fossil fuels to clean energy.
If I go back to that point about climate
change, it's absolutely essential and uh
you can look at various uh you know,
expert views from science and from
energy uh experts that say we have to
find ways to move from fossil fuels to
clean energy in order to bend that curve
and to bring emissions under control.
Many countries, including Cambodia in
our region, still rely on fossil fuels
and coal for a substantial portion of
electricity. And that's something which
we really have to continue to work on
and it will take efforts of energy
regulators, of bankers, and insurance,
and other long-term investors in order
to be able to work toward that energy
transition.
This is an issue not just of the
climate. This is also an issue around
financial risk. So, financing a a fossil
fuel power plant or a coal particularly
coal power plant today, a lot of people
would not want to do that because of
pure risk reasons. That right today,
renewable energy is becoming cheaper
than coal. And so, few years out, either
for climate reasons or pure
competitiveness reasons, that may not be
a viable investment. So, there's an
issue of stranded assets which the
financial system has to manage. So,
financing that energy transition and
finding ways to do that, it will be a
key theme. And it's not just a matter
for the energy sector. It's also a
matter for the entire economy. And the
reason I say this is going back to this
point about ESG,
and many corporations now working very
hard to be able to meet the needs of
those various stakeholders,
greening supply chains becomes one of
the most important themes for many, many
corporations.
And so, going forward for any country
for whom exports is an important part of
economic strategy,
who how green those exports are will
become a competitive issue.
If there's a global supplier of a
product,
it will be looking to find sources of
supply, whether those are raw materials
or components or finished goods, that
are produced with low carbon energy.
This year, the EU-ASEAN Business Council
did its annual business sentiment
survey, and 47%, almost half of the
companies around the region who
responded said they are rethinking their
supply chains. Now, we know that
rethinking supply chains, some of that's
being driven by trade frictions, some by
economics. But one thing they're going
to be thinking about as they choose
their sources of supply
is will this supplier
be able to supply me with green product?
Because I'm going to have to report on
to my shareholders and my other
stakeholders and my investors that my
supplier is green.
So, it's very important for the whole
economy that this issue of energy
transition and sustainability and
sustainable finance to help make this
happen is something we all have to think
about in order to preserve
competitiveness.
And there are, it you know, discussions
being held in Europe today around
whether or not there will be actual
border adjustments, meaning extra
charges added to imports for their
carbon content. Now, that's an issue
being discussed in Europe right now, but
I think if you look at countries even in
our region, China, Japan, Korea,
the there are discussions now about
setting up carbon markets and pricing
carbon. So, I don't think I think within
the decade, we're going to see
very, very serious implications
for competitiveness of industry, for
export industry, around this question of
being able to show we're producing what
we produce in an energy efficient and
green way.
The next thing I will be point out and
it's just been talked about by the
previous panel, so I don't need to labor
it all, is around financial inclusion
and access to financial security. When I
say financial security or health
security or retirement security, I'm
talking about the full range of issues
around financial inclusion.
Um
this goes back to what I said, green
inclusive growth. This is very
fundamental and and it'll be a major
factor in driving it. I was pleased to
see the the statement um
of the Bankers Association around
becoming a leader in the Mekong area in
sustainable finance and financial
inclusion as the core of that. And I'm
sure this conference has been good
illustration of of that importance of
that. And of course, for Prudential, uh
you know, you'll see very clearly our
purpose is to provide access to health
care to everybody. So, the ability to do
that um
collaborating with others in an
inclusive way is fundamental to our
mission.
And finally, my fifth theme is around
transition assistance for affected
workers.
I think this is an area where
it's going to take enormous
collaboration because this when we talk
about the first four trends that are
going to drive sustainable finance and
create needs for us to work with our
customers to make them help them get
through this transition and to make it
possible.
There are going to be business models
and sectors of of an economy which will
have to change. Um and whether that's
because of technological disruption or
because of new climate-friendly
regulations or other other international
competitive reasons, there're going to
have to be transitions.
And the countries I think that'll come
through this best are the ones that can
provide effective transition assistance
efficiently and quickly to workers,
provide credit for starting new
businesses, provide assistance for
communities to reposition the nature of
their economy.
And I think technology will be a great
enabler of that, both for creating the
jobs of the future, but also, for
example, having the ability to retrain,
provide education and training services
digitally to people on a on a very, very
efficient and low-cost basis so that it
makes
retraining and jobs of the future
available to everybody.
Being able to do that is something which
I think is very much fits the spirit and
capabilities of Cambodia. I I wish I
could have visited this year. I couldn't
obviously because of the of the
of the pandemic. But in my many visits
in the past, one of the things that's
impressed me most is is the way that the
country moved can move quickly and the
incredibly talented young workforce and
the innovation that's going on there. I
think the examples of the companies and
and innovations that have come up in
this conference are proof of that.
So, in conclusion, I would just say that
I'm very optimistic um you know, and
with the leadership of the of the
National Bank of Cambodia, the the
Bankers Association, and the many
companies that are involved in this
conference today,
that it's going to be possible for
Cambodia to rise to the occasion and to
benefit from these five themes and to
show real leadership in positioning the
economy that can provide green inclusive
growth for the next decade. And it'll be
a pleasure for to help and collaborate
in that side by side along the way.
Thank you very much for the opportunity
to speak and I wish you the best and
best luck for the panel for taking this
subject further.
Thank you.